<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the honourable the knights, citizens and burgesses of the House of Commons in Parliament assembled The humble petition of the inhabitants of the parishes, of Stepney, Shorditch, VVhitchappell and Algate, the chappelry of Wapping, the precinct of St. Katherins, and the parish of St. Peter Advincula, adjacent to the Tower, and without the liberties of London.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1469</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.4[43]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210696</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869469</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160665</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94495)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160665)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 245:669f4[43])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the honourable the knights, citizens and burgesses of the House of Commons in Parliament assembled The humble petition of the inhabitants of the parishes, of Stepney, Shorditch, VVhitchappell and Algate, the chappelry of Wapping, the precinct of St. Katherins, and the parish of St. Peter Advincula, adjacent to the Tower, and without the liberties of London.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Militia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:160665:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the honourable the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes Of the Houſe of Commons in PARLIAMENT aſſembled. The humble Petition of the Inhabitants of the Pariſhes, of <hi>Stepney, Shorditch, VVhitchappell</hi> and <hi>Algate,</hi> the Chappelgy of <hi>Wapping,</hi> the Precinct of St. <hi>Katherins,</hi> and the Pariſh of St. <hi>Peter Advincula,</hi> adjacent to the <hi>TOWER,</hi> and without the liberties of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT a great part of the Inhabitants of the Places aboveſaid, are <hi>Mariners,</hi> and other Perſons belonging to Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who are often at Sea, or abord their Ships and Veſſells, and ſo their Houſes and Families left deſtitute of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and expoſed to danger in time of any Uproare; Another part of the ſame Inhabitants, are <hi>Trained Souldiers</hi> (bearing their own charges) under the command of the Lieutenant of the <hi>Tower,</hi> at whoſe pleaſure they are called, either in their whole number, or ſeverall ſmaller diviſions of them, both night and day into the <hi>Tower,</hi> to doe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice there, or unto other places remot from their own dwellings, wherby alſo their Houſes and Families are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of defence, and open to like danger in time of any commotion; And the reſidue of the ſaid Inhabitants, are moft Handy-crafts-men, undiſciplined in <hi>Militarie</hi> affaires, not ſet in any order for defence, and thereby as lyable to danger, as any others.</p>
            <p>That the apprehenſions of theſe and greater dangers, are increaſed in the Petitioners, from the grounds and reaſons here under mentioned, which they humbly offer to your grave conſideration: <hi>(viꝪt.)</hi> becauſe</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London</hi> (which the Petitioners formerly accompted a defence and ſafeguard to them) is taken out of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody of Perſons of honour and truſt; a number of Cannoneirs with their Labourers drawne into the ſame, many pretending attendance upon the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> reſide there, the new Warders lately put into the ſame, are many of them Alehouſe-keepers, and moſt of them, of looſe Converſations, yet have great truſt in the <hi>Tower;</hi> and the Trained Souldiers of the Hamlets, who watch in the <hi>Tower,</hi> are confined unto ſtrait places, where, for want of power and number, they can neither prevent any deſperate deſigne, which may poſſibly be attempted, nor be any way ſerviceable, for the defence of the Place.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Divers words (ſome whereof are particularized in the <hi>Schedule</hi> annexed) have been ſpoken, by ſundry Perſons dwelling in the places above ſaid, tending to the diſuniting of the two Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the defamation of divers Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this honourable Houſe, and intimating ſome bloody deſigne in hand, againſt the well affected of the Kingdome, under the names of <hi>Puritans</hi> and <hi>Browniſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. One <hi>Richard Cray,</hi> a new Warder in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and a Conſtable of a large Precinct neere <hi>Wapping,</hi> hath (beſides his dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſpeeches) endeavoured to raiſe men in Armes, to keepe thoſe whom he calls <hi>Puritans</hi> and <hi>Browniſts,</hi> from coming to <hi>Church,</hi> and hath with many others, his partakers, greatly oppoſed, the two worthy Preachers at <hi>Stepney,</hi> Mr. <hi>Burroughs,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Greenhill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. On Thurſday night laſt, when the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> were up in Armes, for their defence, upon the rumor of approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing danger, divers of the Petitioners having Armed themſelves alſo, for their own defence, and being peaceably in their Watch, to prevent further inconvenience, the ſaid <hi>Cray</hi> in a violent manner tooke the Armes from ſome of the Petitioners, threatned the reſt, and ſaid, if he had known, he would have been better provided for them, meaning (as they conceive) either to hurt, unarme, or oppoſe them.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners therefore humbly pray, that they may have Authority from this honourable Aſſembly, freely to put themſelves into a Poſture of defence, for the better enabling of them, to maintaine his <hi>Mateſties</hi> Perſon and Authority, the power and Privileges of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and their own lives, liberties and eſtates, according to their late Proteſtation: And that they may have liberty to that end, to chooſe Officers for their better guidance and inſtruction, to exerciſe themſelves in <hi>Militarie Diſcipline,</hi> and to provide Armes and Amunition, that ſome ſpeedy courſe may be taken for the better ordering of the ſaid <hi>Tower,</hi> and to prevent the dangers by fireworks and otherwiſe, which may ariſe from that place: And that the ſaid <hi>Cray</hi> and others, who have threatned, or oppoſed the Petitioners, may anſwer the matters layd to their charge, and receive ſuch condigne puniſhment as this honourable Aſſembly in your great wiſdomes ſhall thinke fit.</p>
            <closer>And the Petitioners ſhall daily pray, &amp;c.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="schedule">
            <head>The CHEDULE.</head>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>RIchard Cray</hi> a Conſtable of the Pariſh of <hi>Stepney,</hi> and one of the new Warders in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſince the laſt Pacification with the <hi>Scots,</hi> and the happy union betweene theſe two Kingdomes, affirmed that the <hi>Scots,</hi> are all Rogues and Rebells; That he hopes all <hi>Puritans</hi> and <hi>Browniſts</hi> ſhall be worſe hampered, tortured and torne, then ever the <hi>Papiſts</hi> were, and that he himſelfe would helpe to do it, and this he delivered with a great deale of vehemency, ſmiting his hand upon the Table</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mathew Owen</hi> on the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January</hi> inſtant, affirmed, that Mr. <hi>Pym,</hi> and the other foure, did carry two faces under one hood, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> would be quiet enough, if they might be let alone, and that it was long of the <hi>Puritans</hi> that all this ſtir is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Walter</hi> of Lime-houſe, on the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>December</hi> laſt, being asked why the Drum did beat, did enter into many rayling ſpeeches, calling divers people of honeſt report, a company of damned Puritan-whores and rogues, and ſaid he hoped ere long, to ſee all their throates cut, or they hang'd, as thoſe are in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Bungie</hi> affirmed, that he would joyne with the <hi>Papiſts</hi> againſt the <hi>Puritans</hi> and <hi>Browniſts,</hi> if the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſhould riſe.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
